{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Which of the following may be used to measure the rate of nuclear disintegration?", "opta": "Geiger-Muller Counter", "optb": "Cyclotron", "optc": "Cold chamber", "optd": "Mass spectrograph", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The decrease in the atomic number is not observed in case of", "opta": "electron capture", "optb": "\u03b2-emission", "optc": "\u03b1-emission", "optd": "positron emission", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The mass number of an element is not changed, when it emits __________ radiations.", "opta": "\u03b1 & \u03b2", "optb": "\u03b2 & \u03b3", "optc": "\u03b3 & \u03b1", "optd": "\u03b1, \u03b2, & \u03b3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is   not   a   naturally occurring nuclear fuel ?", "opta": "Uranium-238", "optb": "Thorium-233", "optc": "Plutonium-239", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An electron has a mass that is approximately __________ that of the proton.", "opta": "1836 (approximately)", "optb": "1/1836 (approximately)", "optc": "1", "optd": "\u221e", "ans": "B", "explanation": "An electron has a mass that is approximately 1/1836.15267245(75) that of the proton."}, {"question": "Which is the most commonly used molten metal for cooling of nuclear reactors ?", "opta": "Calcium", "optb": "Sodium", "optc": "Mercury", "optd": "Zinc", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The amount of a radioactive material (having a half life of 100 years) remaining after 400 years will be __________ of its original weight.", "opta": "1/2", "optb": "1/4", "optc": "1/8", "optd": "1/16", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The second underground nuclear test was conducted by India at", "opta": "Jaisalmer", "optb": "Pokhran", "optc": "Kalpakkan", "optd": "Narora", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is artificially produced as it does not occur in nature ?", "opta": "Uranium-235", "optb": "Uranium-233", "optc": "Plutonium-239", "optd": "Both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gas cooling as compared to water cooling of nuclear reactors", "opta": "can not attain a high temperature.", "optb": "is more efficient as gas has a higher specific heat.", "optc": "can produce only saturated steam for feeding to power turbine.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The decay product of tritium (a beta emitter) is", "opta": "lithium", "optb": "helium", "optc": "deuterium", "optd": "hydrogen", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heat is generated in a nuclear reactor (thermal) by", "opta": "combustion of a nuclear fuel e.g. uranium.", "optb": "fusion of atoms of uranium.", "optc": "absorption of neutrons in uranium atoms.", "optd": "fission of U-235 by neutrons.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The time taken for a radioactive element to reduce to 50% of its original weight is __________ years, if its half life period is 12 years.", "opta": "24", "optb": "18", "optc": "6", "optd": "36", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following may not need a moderator ?", "opta": "Candu reactor", "optb": "Fast breeder reactor", "optc": "Homogeneous reactor", "optd": "Pressurised water reactor", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The amount of a radioisotope remaining undecayed after a time equal to four times its half life, will be __________ percent.", "opta": "3.125", "optb": "6.25", "optc": "12.50", "optd": "25", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fast breeder reactors do not", "opta": "use Th-232 as fissile fuel.", "optb": "convert fertile material to fissile material.", "optc": "use fast neutrons for fission.", "optd": "use molten sodium as coolant.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thorium-232 is converted into uranium-233 in a/an __________ nuclear reactor.", "opta": "thermal", "optb": "fast breeder", "optc": "heavy water moderated", "optd": "enriched uranium", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following may not need a control rod ?", "opta": "Liquid metal cooled reactor.", "optb": "Fast breeder reactor.", "optc": "Candu reactor.", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One 'amu' is equivalent to", "opta": "9.31 MeV", "optb": "931 eV", "optc": "931 Mev", "optd": "931J", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Commercial power generation from fusion reactor is not yet possible, because", "opta": "it is difficult to control fusion reaction.", "optb": "the fuel required (e.g. deuterium and tritium) is scarce.", "optc": "it is difficult to initiate fusion reaction.", "optd": "quantity of fuel required for initiating fusion reaction is prohibitively high.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Spent fuel from the nuclear thermal reactor contains", "opta": "fission products", "optb": "plutonium", "optc": "unused fuel", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A boiling water reactor is the one, in which the", "opta": "coolant water is allowed to boil in the core of the reactor.", "optb": "coolant water, after being heated in the reactor core, generates steam in a boiler.", "optc": "pressurised water is pumped into the core.", "optd": "fuel and the coolant are thoroughly mixed to form a homogeneous solution.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is used as a coolant in nuclear reactor due to its high capture cross-section ?", "opta": "H2", "optb": "N2", "optc": "He", "optd": "CO2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Moderating material used in a thermal-reactor should be a", "opta": "good absorber of neutrons.", "optb": "solid substance.", "optc": "poor absorber of neutrons.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ordinary water is not used as a moderator because, it", "opta": "has a low absorption cross-section.", "optb": "has a low scattering cross-section.", "optc": "absorbs neutrons.", "optd": "does not absorb neutrons.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The atomic number of a radioactive element is not changed, when it emits __________ rays.", "opta": "\u03b1", "optb": "\u03b2", "optc": "\u03b3", "optd": "\u03b1 & \u03b2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fission of U-235 on slow neutron bombardment can be represented by", "opta": "92U235 + 3 \u03b31  56Ba143 + 36Kr90", "optb": "92U235 + 0n1  56Ba143 + 36Kr90 + 3 0n1", "optc": "92U235 + 0n1  56Ba143 + 36Kr90 + 3 0n1  + Q (energy)", "optd": "92U235 + 0n1  92U236 + 30n1+ Q (energy)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A nuclear reactor can't be used for", "opta": "the production of radioisotopes.", "optb": "supplying intense fields or beams of neutron for scientific experiments.", "optc": "marine ship propulsion.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a moderating material used in nuclear reactor ?", "opta": "Graphite.", "optb": "Cadmium.", "optc": "Zircalloy (an alloy of zirconium and aluminium).", "optd": "Stainless steel.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The atomic number of an element is equal to the number of __________ present in its atom.", "opta": "neutrons", "optb": "electrons", "optc": "protons", "optd": "either (b) or (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not, a fertile material ?", "opta": "Th-232", "optb": "U-238", "optc": "U-233", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Molten sodium (as a coolant in fast breeder reactor)", "opta": "can't attain high temperature at normal pressure.", "optb": "is not at all corrosive, even at a higher temperature.", "optc": "is highly radioactive at elevated temperatures and can cause explosion, when it comes in contact with air or water.", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Final product of uranium extraction plant at Jadugoda (Bihar) is", "opta": "uranium", "optb": "uranium oxide", "optc": "uranium carbide", "optd": "magnesium diuranate", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one is the radioactive isotope of hydrogen ?", "opta": "Deuterium", "optb": "Ortho-hydrogen", "optc": "Tritium", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A homogeneous reactor is the one, in which the", "opta": "fissile atoms are evenly distributed throughout the mass of nuclear reactor.", "optb": "same substance (e.g. heavy water) is used as moderator & coolant.", "optc": "the fuel and the moderator is mixed to form a homogeneous material.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydrogen has __________ isotopes.", "opta": "no", "optb": "one", "optc": "two", "optd": "three", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MeV is the unit of", "opta": "radioactivity", "optb": "energy", "optc": "potential difference", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Velocity of the thermal neutron (< 0.025 eV) used for fission of U-235 is around __________ m/sec.", "opta": "1", "optb": "2200", "optc": "3 x 1011", "optd": "9 x 1021", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Energy equivlant to one atomic mass unit (amu) is __________ MeV.", "opta": "9.31", "optb": "93.1", "optc": "931", "optd": "9310", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"Critical mass\" is the minimum mass of nuclear fissile material required for the", "opta": "sustainment of chain reaction.", "optb": "power generation on commercial scale.", "optc": "economic power generation.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The type of pump used for the recirculation of molten sodium coolant in liquid metal cooled reactor is a/an __________ pump.", "opta": "electromagnetic", "optb": "reciprocating", "optc": "centrifugal", "optd": "volute", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fast breeder Test Reactor (FBTR) is located at", "opta": "Kalpakkam (near Madras).", "optb": "Kota (in Rajasthan).", "optc": "BARC (Trombay).", "optd": "Tarapur (in Maharashtra).", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tarapur atomic power station", "opta": "has two boiling water reactors of American design.", "optb": "has an installed capacity of 400 MW.", "optc": "is the first power reactor in India, which became critical in 1969.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a nuclear explosion, the energy is released primarily in the form of __________ energy-", "opta": "potential", "optb": "thermal", "optc": "kinetic", "optd": "electrical", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The largest stable nucleus is", "opta": "U-235", "optb": "U-238", "optc": "Pb-206", "optd": "Bi-209", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydrogen bomb employs the nuclear fusion of", "opta": "hydrogen", "optb": "deuterium", "optc": "tritium", "optd": "helium", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sodium melts (at atmospheric pressure) at a temperature of __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "58", "optb": "98", "optc": "348", "optd": "588", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of volume of an atom to that of its nucleus is", "opta": "1012", "optb": "10-12", "optc": "10-8", "optd": "108", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Research reactors are normally meant for", "opta": "producing high neutron flux 1012-1013 neutrons/cm2, sec and studying the effect of neutron bombardment on dif ferent materials.", "optb": "accelerating the neutrons.", "optc": "power generation.", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Out of the followingplaces, a nuclear power plant is not located at", "opta": "Talcher (Orissa)", "optb": "Kaiga (Karnataka)", "optc": "Rawatbhata (Rajsthan)", "optd": "Kalpakkam (Tamilnadu)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}